HENRIQUE ALVES PESCIOTTI

- PERSONAL DETAILS -

Brazilian/ Italian

29 South Parade, Waterford, Co. Waterford

+353 (87) 265 1702

hpesciotti@gmail.com

LinkedIn:

www.linkedin.com/in/henriqu e-pesciotti-694404134

- SKILLS -

Attention to Detail
Teamwork
Field Investigation Skills
Customer Service
Project Management

· LANGUAGES ·

Portuguese - Native

English

Listening	C1
Reading	C1
Spoken Interaction	C1
Spoken Production	C1
Writing	B2

French

Listening	В1
Reading	B2
Spoken Interaction	A2
Spoken Production	A2
Writing	A1

DIGITAL COMPETENCE

Good command of Office Suite, including MS Project, ArcGIS and QGIS

Basic knowledge of Python and R

PROFILE

Geographer experienced in project management, coordination, and development of environmental feasibility and licensing studies. I have worked in various segments (such as mining, infrastructure, and urban development) throughout Brazil, for the last 12 years,

with a proven record of more than sixty projects.

EMPLOYMENT HISTORY

Project Manager at Lume Estratégia Ambiental

November 2018 - May 2022

Manage and monitor the projects schedule, budget, and products/deliverables (environmental reports); Prepare commercial proposals/tenders, predicting needed resources, budget, and scope; Meeting internal and external stakeholders to align expectations, content, tasks, risks, and billing events; Maintain a close relationship with the client, alerting, negotiating, and solving timeline issues.

Project Coordinator at Lume Estratégia Ambiental

September 2016 - November 2018

Set the scope and manage a team of multidisciplinary specialists in environmental feasibility and environmental licensing projects in various segments, such as mining, infrastructure, urban equipment, and industry. Develop in conjunction with the stakeholders (engineering companies/mining companies) the site context and description in an effort to set the basis for the team to assess environmental impacts.

Technical Coordinator at Lume Estratégia Ambiental

April 2014 - September 2016

Technical coordination and elaboration of surveys related to the physical landscape (water resources, air quality, soil, relief, geology, noise, and vibration). Writing, reviewing and consolidating reports encompassing diagnostics, prognostics, and mitigation programs, similar in scope to Environmental Impact Assessment (EIA) reports.

Environmental Analyst at Lume Estratégia Ambiental

January 2012 - April 2014

Conduction of diagnostics and prognostics related to the physical environment through field-acquired data (assessing and collecting samples). In addition to performing geoprocessing routines and elaborating thematic maps.

Undergraduate Researcher at Universidade Federal de Minas Gerais - UFMG

July 2009 – August 2010

Fellowship of scientific initiation, studying springs in urban parks, entitled: "Nascentes em Unidades de Conservação de Belo Horizonte - MG: Levantamento, Espacialização e Caracterização Ambiental".

EDUCATION

 Postgraduate degree in Integrated Environmental Engineering, Instituto de Educação Tecnológica, IETEC, Belo Horizonte, Brazil (NFQ Level 9)

January 2012 – January 2013

 BA, Geography, Universidade Federal de Minas Gerais - UFMG, Belo Horizonte, Brazil (NFQ Level 8)

January 2008 - January 2012

Environmental Consulting

The selected cases are part of a portfolio composed of 65 projects with proven experience through technical annotation of responsibility (Anotação de Responsabilidade Técnica - ART) issued by the Regional Council of Engineering and Agronomy (Conselho Regional de Engenharia e Agronomia – CREA).

1. SECOND EXPASION OF BAÚ MINE, 2021 - 2022

Keywords: Environmental Permits, Project Management, Mining

Brief description: The project aimed to expand Baú mining compound's iron ore production from 950 thousand tons to 1.5 million tons annually. MR Mineração, the developer, planned to expand specific mine sections and upgrade the ore processing unit. As project manager, I collaborated with planning and environmental sectors to establish a timeline, scope, and deliverables, aiming to obtain the necessary environmental permit for the expansion. The key challenges included managing a tight schedule, client expectations, and environmental surveys. The success of the Second Expansion relied on a dynamic, detailed plan, and efficient management.

2. SERRA DA MOEDA WILDLIFE'S CORRIDOR, 2018

Keywords: Wildlife Corridors, GIS, Conservation

Brief description: The project was initiated by the local public prosecutor's office to address landscape maintenance and conservation in Serra da Moeda. It involved proposing a wildlife corridor spanning approximately 117 km in a mountainous area to facilitate genetic exchange between forest and grassland fragments affected by iron ore mining. The corridor was developed using Geographical Information System (GIS) tools and involved identifying main and secondary corridors to connect various fragments in the region. The methodology included GIS analysis, statistical kernel normalization, and the involvement of experts in selecting variables and barriers. The project also used satellite imagery and the Random Forest algorithm to survey land cover and use. The project lead coordinator managed a multidisciplinary team of over 20 experts and conducted GIS routines and on-site verifications.

3. EXPANSION BAÚ MINE, 2016

Keywords: Environmental Impact Assessment (EIA), Physical Environment, Mining

Brief description: The project involved conducting an environmental impact study for the expansion of iron ore mining in the Socorro district of Barão de Cocais, MG. The current mining facility covers around 50 hectares, and the expansion project aims to add another 200 hectares. As the coordinator of the physical aspects of the landscape the focus was on assessing geomorphology, hydrogeography, and pedology. Special attention was given to intermittent lagoons in the nearby mountain ridge known as "Quadrilátero Ferrifero," which are considered sinkholes resulting from itabirite dissolution. Historical aerial imagery was used to study the hydrographic regime and the contributing areas of these ponds. Field surveys determined the regolith type and local water table depth. The study evaluated potential impacts of mining operations on the hydrological and sedimentological dynamics of these pseudo-karstic features. As part of the prognosis, suggested parameters and a monitoring network were proposed to ensure the auality of surface water.

4. PACUERA PCHs: Glória - Muriaé/MG; Nova Maurício - Leopoldina/MG; Mello — Rio Preto/MG, 2014 - 2016

Keywords: land and water use planning and zoning

Brief description: The objective of these studies was to develop a territorial planning plan for three small-scale hydroelectric power plants. The plan focused on the reservoir and its surrounding areas within a 250-meter radius. Satellite imagery and fieldwork were used to determine zoning regulations to accommodate existing land and water uses while ensuring efficient electricity generation. The zoning adhered to regulations set by the Brazilian Navy, as well as municipal, state, and federal laws. Challenges arose, including conflicts with industrial-scale pig farming near one reservoir, leading to eutrophication and the proliferation of aquatic macrophytes. As the technical and executive coordinator, I conducted the zoning and use survey. The proposed plan was subjected to public hearings for community input, and relevant information provided by residents was incorporated into the final zoning decisions.

5. Technical, Economic, and Environmental Feasibility Study - Railroads - 2013 - 2014

Keywords: Environmental Feasibility, map algebra, railroads

Brief description: The study was part of a public-private initiative to expand the railroad network in Brazil. It focused on technical, economic, and environmental feasibility over five thousand kilometers of railroad. I acted as a geoprocessing coordinator, managing a team that responsible for creating a database to aid in route design, incorporating environmental constraints through map algebra and a multidisciplinary approach. This allowed the engineering company to consider various environmental factors alongside topographic maps. Identifying and mapping traditional communities, conservation units, and potential cave locations was one of the tasks. I played a crucial role in developing and implementing the project's methodology. Additionally, I took part of meetings between the engineering and environmental teams in which through an AHP matrix, with environmental aspects carrying a 40% weight one of three evaluated alternatives was chosen.

Bibliographic Production

Papers in Scientific Journals

FELIPPE, M. F.; MAGALHAES JR, A.; PESCIOTTI, H. A.; COELI, L. Nascentes Antropogênicas: Processos Tecnogênicos e Hidrogeomorfológicos. Revista Brasileira de Geomorfológia, v.14, p.279 - 286, 2013.

Home page: https://rbgeomorfologia.org.br/rbg/article/view/210

Title in English: ANTHROPOGENIC SPRINGS: TECHNOGENICAL AND HYDROGEOMORPHOLOGICAL PROCESSES

Book Chapter's Published

LAVARINI, C.; PESCIOTTI, H. A.; COELI, L.; MAGALHAES JR, A. Hydrosedimentology of Natural Streams and it's Relevance to Artificial Streams: The Study of Córrego Ponte Queimada - Belo Horizonte/MG In: Research Award for Young Scholars 2011 - "Adaptive Water Management: looking to the future".1 ed. Rio de Janeiro: FGV Direito Rio, 2011, v.1, p. 7-94.

Home page: http://direitorio.fgv.br/publicacoes/research-award-for-young-scholars-2011-adaptive-water-management-looking-to-the-future

Papers in international events (complete)

PESCIOTTI, H. A.; COELI, L.; LAVARINI, C.; FELIPPE, M. F.; MAGALHAES JR, A. Estudo Morfológico e Ambiental de Nascentes em Parques Urbanos de Belo Horizonte - MG. In: VIII Simpósio Nacional De Geomorfologia - I Encontro Latino Americano De Geomorfologia - I Encontro Ibero-Americano De Geomorfologia - I Encontro Ibero-Americano Do Quaternário, 2010, Recife - PE.

Title in English: Morphological and Environmental Study of Stream Springs In Belo Horizonte - MG's Urban Parks

COELI, L.; ANDRADE, C. F.; **PESCIOTTI, H. A.**; LAVARINI, C.; ARAUJO, B. A Ação do Homem como Agente Geológico-Geomorfológico: estudo de caso do Município de Ouro Preto – MG. In: VIII Simpósio Nacional De Geomorfologia - I Encontro Latino Americano De Geomorfologia - I Encontro Ibero-Americano Do Quaternário, Recife - PE. VIII Simpósio Nacional De Geomorfologia - I Encontro Latino Americano De Geomorfologia - I Encontro, 2010.

Title in English: Anthropic Action as a Geological-Geomorphological Agent: The Study of Ouro Preto - MG

LAVARINI, C.; PESCIOTTI, H. A.; COELI, L.; MAGALHAES JR, A. Dinâmica Hidrossedimentológica e Ambientes de Calha Fluvial em um Curso D'água Serrano: o Caso do Córrego Ponte Queimada - Belo Horizonte/MG. In: VIII Simpósio Nacional De Geomorfologia - I Encontro Latino Americano de Geomorfologia - I Encontro Ibero-Americano Do Quaternário, 2010, Recife - PE.

Title in English: Hydrosyssedimentological Dynamics and Fluvial Environments in Mountain Catchment: The Study of Ponte Queimada Stream - Belo Horizonte / MG.